Roy Chancellor

2014 East Anderson Drive, Phoenix, Arizona 85022

roychance600@gmail.com

480.242.6356

SUMMARY

Systems-minded, highly-organized software developer building upon a foundation in mechanical engineering and mathematics education and 2+ years of experience in Java and C programming. Fueled by a deep desire to solve difficult problems with clean, maintainable code. Thrive in organizations that value technical excellence and provide mentoring.

SKILLS

- **Core Java**: Four semesters (16 credit-hours) of core Java object-oriented programming emphasizing back-end database applications, agile, and SDLC
- **C/C++**: Experience writing code to acquire and display data from A/D cards, communicate through RS-232, simulate dynamic systems, and control electronic devices
- **RESTful APIs**: Developed and modified APIs using the MuleSoft integration platform; earned Mule 4 Developer Cert.
- Web services: Developed web-based Java banking application with object-oriented class structures and MVC design
 pattern using Eclipse / Maven, JUnit tests, JavaDocs, CRUD database functions using SQL through JDBC, and hosted in
 the cloud on AWS Elastic Beanstalk with RDS database
- Agile: Created a Java vending machine management system with a lean and fast team using agile scrum by developing user stories, planning sprints, managing backlog, and running daily stand-ups; familiar with SDLC
- Front-end: Working knowledge of HTML / CSS to create web pages and vanilla JavaScript DOM manipulation
- Python: Basic skills acquired through an online course
- **Courses**: Java Programming I, II, and III, Open Source Computing, C Programming, Introduction to Numerical Methods, Mechatronics (embedded control)
- Familiar technologies: Eclipse, Maven, git, GitHub, SQL, JDBC, REST, JAX-RS, AWS cloud (EC2, Elastic Beanstalk, RDS), JUnit, Spring, SDLC, data structures, MuleSoft APIs

MECHANICAL AND MANUFACTURING ENGINEERING CAREER

15 years developing and improving products across their entire life cycle (R&D through full-scale production)

Problem Solving

- Eliminated shock-induced PCB cracking in a rocket controller by designing a unique stiffener that enabled flight qualification on schedule
- Increased machine uptime by >20% by developing a program to send machine-down alerts to operators
- Drove customer complaints for low brightness of automotive EL lamps to zero by applying binary problem solving

Six Sigma Master Black Belt

- Led a corporate-level team of black belts that completed high-visibility projects across the company netting more than \$1M savings over 3 years
- Solved and prevented numerous quality problems across the product life cycle that led to increased yield and happier customers

MATHEMATICS EDUCATION CAREER

11 years classroom teaching and school leadership recognized for extreme organization, strong leadership, and clear communication

- Saved uncountable hours of teacher preparation by creating open-source math curricula spanning Algebra 1 through Calculus 2, including all lesson plans, assessments, and pacing calendars
- Designed the annual master school schedule by solving dozens of logic conflicts and validating with custom VBA code before deployment
- Managed the school web site by creating unique content and organizing operational documents and links that saved teachers time hunting for information in many places
- Mentored math teachers, including one who became a master teacher

WORK EXPERIENCE

9/2019 - PRESENT

ASSOCIATE SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENT ENGINEER, Hawaiian Airlines, Tempe, AZ

- Create RESTful APIs using MuleSoft to package, transform, and deliver source data to a matrix of internal customers
- Earned MuleSoft developer certification (Mule 4)

7/2015 - 6/2019

MASTER TEACHER OF MATHEMATICS [Great Hearts Academies, Phoenix, AZ

- Designed and delivered highly-interactive mathematics lessons using the Socratic method and high energy
- Organized and led all internal school operations for an 850-student academy including creating the master schedule of classes that solved myriad conflicts and running state-mandated testing (2015-2017)
- Developed honors-level math curricula that are turn-key ready for new teachers to adopt and modify
- Analyzed state testing data to drive instructional improvements in core mathematics and English courses

(RETURNED TO ARIZONA TO TAKE MASTER MATH TEACHER POSITION)

6/2013 - 7/2015

MANUFACTURING ENGINEER, Schweitzer Engineering Laboratories, Pullman, WA

- Synthesized requirements from R&D engineers, process engineers, and manufacturing operations to introduce new circuit boards and product assemblies into production and make significant upgrades to existing products
- Solved chronic manufacturing problems on legacy and new products by partnering with product mechanical engineers to design, validate, and release permanent solutions

(SABBATICAL FROM TEACHING TO ENGINEERING POSITION IN WASHINGTON)

8/2008 - 5/2013

MASTER TEACHER OF MATHEMATICS, Great Hearts Academies, Phoenix, AZ

- Shaped the honors-level math curriculum during the start-up years of a high-performing charter school
- Designed and delivered highly-interactive mathematics lessons that incorporated the Socratic method

8/2006 - 5/2008

MATHEMATICS TEACHER, Scottsdale Unified School District, Scottsdale, AZ

- Created a highly-practical Business Math course that gave at-risk students valuable real-life math skills
- Taught Geometry to high school sophomores using interactive PowerPoint lessons

(CAREER CHANGE TO FULL-TIME MATHEMATICS EDUCATION)

12/2005 – 7/2006

STATISTICIAN, Intel Corporation, Chandler, AZ

- Delivered statistical and technical expertise to microprocessor packaging engineers that included designing experiments, making sense out of complex data, and driving problems to resolution before production:
- Taught multi-week statistical courses to diverse groups engineers, scientists, and technicians with high ratings for clarity, passion, and direct application to students' jobs

9/1999 - 12/2005

SIX SIGMA MASTER BLACK BELT, Rogers Corporation, Chandler, AZ

- Led and coached teams that solved yield and defect problems and implemented corrective/preventative action for high performance circuit board, electroluminescent (EL) lamp, and polyurethane foam products
- Actively drove Six Sigma into the product development cycle to reduce the risk of quality spills before launch

8/1998 - 7/1999

MECHANICAL ENGINEER, Orbital Sciences Corporation, Chandler, AZ

- Completed analytical and experimental projects to improve the reliability of electronic packages that control all flight operations of rockets
- Performed fatigue analysis of all production-tested flight units to ensure remaining life was sufficient for flight

5/1994 - 8/1998

PROCESS ENGINEER, W.L. Gore and Associates, Phoenix, AZ

- Characterized and improved processes for high-volume production of micro-coax and micro-ribbon cable products used in ultrasound medical devices and disk drives
- Created process science that fused mechanical engineering principles with experimental results to kill defects

12/1993 – 5/1994

TEST PROGRAMMER, E.F. Data Corporation, Tempe, AZ

Reduced satellite modem testing time by 50% by writing a suite of C-language programs to automate test functions

EDUCATION

CERTIFICATE IN JAVA PROGRAMMING (9/2019)

Grand Canyon University, Phoenix, AZ

- 16-credit hours of core Java language and object-oriented principles emphasizing back-end database applications
- Framework and tools: Eclipse, Maven, JDBC, Hibernate, JPA, SQL, AWS, REST, Spring MVC, Spring Boot, JUnit, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, React, git, GitHub
- Immersed in the full software development life cycle (SDLC) using agile scrum methodology

GRADUATE CERTIFICATE IN STATISTICS (5/2004)

Rochester Institute of Technology, Rochester, NY

• Developed theoretical and practical skills in regression analysis and modeling, time series and forecasting, product reliability, and design of experiments

MASTER OF SCIENCE IN MECHANICAL ENGINEERING (12/1993)

Texas A&M University, College Station, TX

- Thesis: Parameter Identification Using Nonlinear Dynamics and Chaos (article published in the ASME Journal of Vibration and Acoustics, July 1996)
- Wrote thousands of lines of C code that simulated dynamic systems, acquired data from electronic devices, processed data using FFT, and graphically displayed data
- Co-created a micro controller-based active-damping system for a 1/4 car suspension by writing embedded C code that implemented PID control

BACHELOR OF SCIENCE IN MECHANICAL ENGINEERING (12/1991)

Arizona State University, Tempe, AZ

• Relevant courses: Introduction to C Programming, Numerical Analysis, Control Systems Analysis